<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research on ScholCommsProd</title>
    <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/categories/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research on ScholCommsProd</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/categories/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Belmont Forum Round Table - data accessibility statements</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2018/10/19/belmont_forum_round_table_-_data_accessibility_statements_/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2018/10/19/belmont_forum_round_table_-_data_accessibility_statements_/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I attended a round table discussion hosted by the Belmont Forum about the release of their position on data accessibility statements and digital objects management plans. (It’s a bit of a mouthful, but the reason is that they are aiming to be clear and comprehensive around what they are asking to make it easier for researchers, publishers and other stakeholders to get to compliance around this policy.)
You can read their position paper — Draft DAS Statement and Policy for October 2018 Plenary - Google Docs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distill is dedicated to making machine learning clear and dynamic</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2018/06/29/distill_is_dedicated_to_making_machine_learning_clear_and_dynamic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2018/06/29/distill_is_dedicated_to_making_machine_learning_clear_and_dynamic/</guid>
      <description>Distill is an experiment in bringing interactive documents and scholarly documents together. I&amp;rsquo;m often asked what the future of publishing might look like, and were we to embrace what the web offers it might look like distill.
Two things though, make it look like a nice product. Right now paper flow into this journal is very low, and secondly they have advertised a large prize to attract work in this format.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>