<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Open Access on ScholCommsProd</title>
    <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/categories/open-access/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Open Access on ScholCommsProd</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/categories/open-access/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Unpaywall Journals - possibly the most interesting thing to happen this year in library subscription land.</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2019/11/06/unpaywall_journals_-_possibly_the_most_interesting_thing_to_happen_this_year_in_library_subscription_land._/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2019/11/06/unpaywall_journals_-_possibly_the_most_interesting_thing_to_happen_this_year_in_library_subscription_land._/</guid>
      <description>Heather and Jason from https://ourresearch.org/ have just released a preview of their new tool - unpaywall journals. You can have a look at the preview of this tool now - Unpaywall Journals.
They previewed this two weeks ago at FORCE2019 and have clearly gone through a ton of work to get the tool the state it is in todday, so big congraatulations to them on the product release.
For those of you not in the know they have a long track record of building useful open infrastructure in the scholarly communications spaace.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PLOS are looking for a new CEO</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2017/01/10/plos-ceo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2017/01/10/plos-ceo/</guid>
      <description>So I hear that PLOS are looking for a new CEO. They are making the process fairly open, so if you are interested you can read more here.
I got to thinking about some of the challenges and opportunities facing PLOS over the weekend. Over the years I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten to know a lot of PLOS folk, and I think it&amp;rsquo;s an amazing organisation. It has proved the viability of open access, and their business model is being copied by a lot of other publishers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What we mean when we talk about preprints</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2016/12/13/when-we-talk-about-preprints/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2016/12/13/when-we-talk-about-preprints/</guid>
      <description>Cameron Neylon, Damian Pattinson, Geoffrey Bilder, and Jennifer Lin have just posted a cracker of a preprint onto biorxiv.
On the origin of nonequivalent states: how we can talk about preprints
 Increasingly, preprints are at the center of conversations across the research ecosystem. But disagreements remain about the role they play. Do they &amp;ldquo;count&amp;rdquo; for research assessment? Is it ok to post preprints in more than one place? In this paper, we argue that these discussions often conflate two separate issues, the history of the manuscript and the status granted it by different communities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>thoughts on the ERC data workshop</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2014/09/24/erc-workshop-thought/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2014/09/24/erc-workshop-thought/</guid>
      <description>On Thursday and Friday of last week I attended a European Research Council workshop on managing research data. It was well attended with about 130 participants brining views from across the academic disciplines. I&amp;rsquo;ve blogged my raw notes from day one and day two. In this post I reflect on the points I noticed that were raised over the two days. People have been talking about the increasing importance of research information for many years now, and a hope was raised in the opening comments that we might be able to provide solutions to the problems posed by the issues of research data, by the end of the workshop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ERC data management workshop, day 1</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2014/09/21/erc-workshop-day1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2014/09/21/erc-workshop-day1/</guid>
      <description>initial thoughts about the workshop.  Opening remarks. Setting the scene. Sabrina Leonelli - the epistemology of data-intesive science. Dr Hans Pfeiffenberger - Open Science &amp;ndash; opportunities, challenges &amp;hellip; @datasciencefeed. Bernd Pulverer - finding and accessing the data behind figures. Dr Roar Skålin - Norwegian researchers want to share, but are afraid of jeopardising their career. Summary of points from the scene setting. Afternoon breakout session - Life Sciences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ERC data management workshop, day 2</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2014/09/21/erc-workshop-day2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2014/09/21/erc-workshop-day2/</guid>
      <description>Life sciences breakout - key points. Physical sciences breakout - key points. Humanities breakout - key points. Open discussion on morning presentations. Breakout session on incentives.  Paul Ayris - Implementing the Future: the LERU roadmap for research data. Sünje Dallmeier‐Tiessen - Incentives for Open Science Attribution, Recognition, Collaboration. Veerle Van den Eynden and Libby Bishop - Incentives for sharing research data, evidence from an EU study. Open discussion after breakout session.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STM brainstorming session - 2013</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2013/12/03/stm-brainstorming-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2013/12/03/stm-brainstorming-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Just attended the STM brainstroming session. I&amp;rsquo;ll update these notes in due course, and fix spelling issues, but I wanted to get the post live first.
Notes I&amp;rsquo;ll just mention the things that I found interesting. ## Round1
Science Gists get a mention, yay!!
Google scholar library gets a mention.
Visualising data as maps is mentioned, mentions that there are no standards
Howard mentions much richer tagging in the article, and upfront semantic tagging.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EC consultation on Open Data - a report.</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2013/07/02/ec-open-data-consultation-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2013/07/02/ec-open-data-consultation-report/</guid>
      <description>This is a report on todays consultation on open data that was help by the EC. The notes are long, so I have put my conclusions and general comments at the start.
General comments There was not much disagreement throughout the day. There were repeated calls for the need to incentivise researchers to engage in data sharing, but not too many concrete proposals on how to do this. It does seem from my perspective that libraries could do an amazing job here, but that will depend on to which extent these libraries have deep technical expertise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EC consultation on Open Data - my presentation.</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2013/07/02/ec-open-data-consultation-our-view/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2013/07/02/ec-open-data-consultation-our-view/</guid>
      <description>The following is the written representation that I made to the EC hearing on Open Data on behalf of Co-Action publishers, Copernicus Publications, eLife, F1000 Research, FigShare, Frontiers, Open Books Publishers, PeerJ, the Public Library of Science, Ubiquity Press and Bloomsbury Qatar Foundation Journals (QScience). I had a five minute slot to present, and the key recommendations at the end of this written response formed the basis of that presentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ENCODE - an example of open publication and data integration.</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2013/01/30/euan-birney-data-publishing-talk-plos-elife/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2013/01/30/euan-birney-data-publishing-talk-plos-elife/</guid>
      <description>On Monday the 14th of January we met at the PLOS offices in Cambridge to hear a talk from Euan Birney on lessons learned from publishing data rich publications though the encode project.
This was the first time that Euan was far less worried about the print, and far more worried about how well the online version was going to work.
Dimensions of the project  5 TeraBases 1715 times the size of the Human Genome 3k experiments 410 authors on the main paper 6 high profile papers ~35 companion papers  The output should not be thought of as papers, but as the raw data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going for gold, open access debate.</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2012/10/02/icoa-going-for-gold/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2012/10/02/icoa-going-for-gold/</guid>
      <description>Update, audio of the meeting is now available on figshare
Last Thursday I attended the SciCommForum debate &amp;ldquo;Open access: going for gold?&amp;rdquo; held at Imperial College. Below are my notes from the event. The notes are fairly raw, and not comprehensive.
The debate is going to be looking at open access in the context of the RCUK policy, it is being hosted by Richard Van Noorden (RVN), Mark Thorley (MT) from RCUK, and Stephen Curry (SC).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The cost of production</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2012/07/12/the-cost-of-production/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2012/07/12/the-cost-of-production/</guid>
      <description>Last week an interesting discussion on the cost of copy editing popped up over on Stephen Curry&amp;rsquo;s blog. In addition the comment thread at the recent Science editorial seems to make this post somewhat timely. I used to manage the copy editing of a good portion of physical science related content from Springer from 2002 &amp;ndash; 2005. I&amp;rsquo;m also currently in the process of setting up a new online-only journal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Thoughts on Peer Review and Altmetrics</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2012/06/18/some-thought-on-peerreview-and-altmetrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2012/06/18/some-thought-on-peerreview-and-altmetrics/</guid>
      <description>The upcoming altmetrics meeting, and a submitted abstract by Kelli Barr prompted me to note down some of my own thoughts on peer review and altmetrics. I would love to make it over to the meeting, but with just a few days now before my first child is born, it ain&amp;rsquo;t gonna happen.
I&amp;rsquo;ve not read Kelly&amp;rsquo;s paper, but after reading the abstract my take home message from it would be something along the lines of &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t replace peer review with altmetrics because you will just replace one bias with another, and at least with peer review the bias is contained within the academic community&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Augmented Peer Review</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2012/06/17/proposal-on-peer-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2012/06/17/proposal-on-peer-review/</guid>
      <description>Last year I was asked to contribute to a special issue on the evolution of peer review. I got quite excited about doing this, but then realised that I really didn&amp;rsquo;t have the time to write a paper. I&amp;rsquo;m not a practicing academic, I build products, and while at Mendeley I really had far too much on my plate to find the time to write up a paper. However the topic does interest me, and I am a strong believer that web scale technologies can help with the scientific communication process though a large number of avenues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hindawi have an awesome reviewing system.</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2011/10/06/hindawi-reviewing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2011/10/06/hindawi-reviewing/</guid>
      <description>Hindawi publishers is a really interesting outfit. They are an open access only publisher based in Egypt. They combing a fantastic use of technology with the ability to afford a large amount of human curation over the data that they use to streamline their publication and reviewing systems.
One of their publishing vehicles is called the International Scholarly Research Network and at the recent coasp conference Paul Peters gave an overview of how their peer review system works, I think it&amp;rsquo;s genius.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Megajournals</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2011/10/03/megajournals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2011/10/03/megajournals/</guid>
      <description>The idea of megajournals had not really formalised in my head before, but at the COASP meeting the talk was all about &amp;ldquo;Megajournals&amp;rdquo;. [PLoSOne][plosone] is the archetype for this kind of journal, and it had not really struck me before as a huge revolution in the publishing industry, but after listening to a couple of days worth of talks on the topic I&amp;rsquo;m convincible.
Megajournals are so called because they are structured to be able to publish many more articles than has been the normal practice with traditional journals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The rude health of Open Access Publishing.</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2011/10/03/coasp-impressions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2011/10/03/coasp-impressions/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR OA publishing is maturing with a scalable business model that all the big publishers are jumping all over. Money will be made (but less than before), and more content will be more open. The poor lamentable nay-sayers who carp on unheard in the darkness will be forgotten, and their Cassandra-like predictions will fade to be recalled as little more than the mutterings of fools (OK, that last bit is probably opinion).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>