<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Open Science on ScholCommsProd</title>
    <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/categories/open-science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Open Science on ScholCommsProd</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/categories/open-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Belmont Forum Round Table - data accessibility statements</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2018/10/19/belmont_forum_round_table_-_data_accessibility_statements_/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2018/10/19/belmont_forum_round_table_-_data_accessibility_statements_/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I attended a round table discussion hosted by the Belmont Forum about the release of their position on data accessibility statements and digital objects management plans. (It’s a bit of a mouthful, but the reason is that they are aiming to be clear and comprehensive around what they are asking to make it easier for researchers, publishers and other stakeholders to get to complicance around this policy.)
You can read their position paper — Draft DAS Statement and Policy for October 2018 Plenary - Google Docs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A(peeling) Peer Review, a proposal.</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2015/05/17/peer-review-idea/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2015/05/17/peer-review-idea/</guid>
      <description>eLife&amp;rsquo;s peer review process is really good. One of the key attributes of this is that reviewers are not blind to one another, and they have to consult with one another. This largely removes the third reviewer problem. We also publish the decision letters and the author responses to the decision letter.
Reviewers have the option of revealing themselves to authors. As with most review systms our reviewers know who the authors are.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>