<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>conference on ScholCommsProd</title>
    <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/categories/conference/</link>
    <description>Recent content in conference on ScholCommsProd</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/categories/conference/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>PLOS ALM 13 day 2</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2013/10/17/plos-alm-13-day2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2013/10/17/plos-alm-13-day2/</guid>
      <description>Connecting ALM and Literature As I took part in the first session I don&amp;rsquo;t have many notes from it. I&amp;rsquo;ve posted the slides from my talk, and I&amp;rsquo;ll write up some more on those in due course. For me the standout talk of the session, if not the entire meeting, was from Jevin West who talked about using networked ranked data to provide recommendations. The algorithms his group are working on are being tested on [SSRN][ssrn], and will be rolled out to PLOS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PLOS ALM 13, day1</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2013/10/16/plos-aml-13-day1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2013/10/16/plos-aml-13-day1/</guid>
      <description>## Cameron Neylon - Introduction &amp;amp; Welcome
Interesting - this is the first PLOS ALM meeting that is a &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; scheduled presentation. Time is going to be tight.
Pete Binfield ALM: Looking back, moving forward A large chunk of OA does not select for impact - this is why ALMs are key for this space. PLOS didn&amp;rsquo;t invent ALMs - Frontiers were doing it a little ahead of PLOS&amp;rsquo;s launch. Web of science didn&amp;rsquo;t tell PLOS until 2010 that PLOS one was being tracked for an impact factor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The rude health of Open Access Publishing.</title>
      <link>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2011/10/03/coasp-impressions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scholarly-comms-product-blog.com/2011/10/03/coasp-impressions/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR OA publishing is maturing with a scalable business model that all the big publishers are jumping all over. Money will be made (but less than before), and more content will be more open. The poor lamentable nay-sayers who carp on unheard in the darkness will be forgotten, and their Cassandra-like predictions will fade to be recalled as little more than the mutterings of fools (OK, that last bit is probably opinion).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>